do
so
[Music]
good evening good day everybody uh
great to be back with you all welcome to
the 77th live episode of ask abhijeet
um and today it's going to be a slightly
shorter episode i've got a bad throat so
i'm going to keep it around 60 75
minutes
so let us see all who all is here i can
see sagar aryan anurag gaurav ayan
good evening good day to all of you nice
to be back among your midst
and let us get going
let's get straight into the questions
with uh question number one let's find
various question number one
what is question number one the question
number one is by ayan chakravarti
is
or rather was the manuscript modified by
british people
so you know what i haven't uh studied
the manuscript in any great detail and
whatever i've seen is uh
small pieces here and there snippets
all english translations and these
english translations that we uh have
were mostly done either by british
people or during british
during the british occupation of india
and therefore one cannot take these
translations
to be the authoritative versions of the
manus mirti because we know that there's
always
even if the translator
has good intentions there's always a
loss in translation sanskrit is a very
nuanced language english is a
one-dimensional language
and when you translate things from
sanskrit to english you're going to end
up losing context and meaning for
instance
the word yagya yagna
is translated as sacrifices in english
but in english sacrifice means killing
something
a yagna is not killing anything but
yagna is always translated as sacrifice
similarly these people they translate
dasa as slave which is nonsense
dharma is religion which is again
nonsense and so on so you know there's
gonna be a lot of loss in translation
and you're gonna lose the original
context in meaning and therefore
even if some translations were done with
good intentions they are going to end up
uh
miss portraying misrepresenting the
actual original text
so uh
and in some cases you may have
genuine i mean deliberate uh
distortions that are introduced into the
text by the translator
so
the
uh thing i'm gonna say
what i'm gonna what i'm trying to say is
that you cannot rely upon translations
of the manuspriti into english
what's more reliable is translations
from the original sanskrit into indian
languages that is way more reliable
because indian languages do preserve
some significant amount of the
context and nuance that sanskrit has
so a better way to study the manuscript
would be to look at the
indian language translation side either
into hindi or some other indian language
the best way to study the manuspati is
to look at the original sanskrit text in
case
you have an understanding and knowledge
of sanskrit
so that's what i can say is it modified
by british people well i haven't studied
in great detail i am not a scholar of
the manuspriti so i can't answer for
sure but there is a high probability
that certain
deliberate mistranslations
would certainly have
been introduced into the text into the
translation especially if it was done by
british people or by let's say marxist
leftist historians
therefore one must be very careful while
studying the text
yogesh says why steve jobs mark jacobs
and many more successful people came to
india
and what did they learn
i don't know about marc jacobs
i'm aware of the fact that steve jobs
did come to india so steve jobs came to
india
i think in the 1970s early 1970s
and he came with the purpose of seeking
spiritual
enlightenment that's why he came to
india
so he was a spiritually inclined person
and he was also dabbling in various
psychedelic drugs lsd etc when he was a
student in the us
and
so he wanted
the real deal not the chemical
experiences so he came to india i think
he came to india searching for the the
the spiritual guru
whose name was neem karoli baba
and i believe that by the time steve
jobs reached india neem karoli baba had
already passed away
and then he wandered around india for a
few months seven eight months i believe
he got exposure to some other gurus
uh
he got some exposure to to
buddhist practices etc
the main source of inspiration for him
was i think neem karoli baba after he
left india he also got exposed when he
back when went back to the us
he got exposed to dhyana meditation or
which is now the one is known as zen
meditation
so all of these influences all dharmic
influences
uh they
formed the core of a spiritual
outlook for the rest of his life
and
so that's what i can say uh i don't i'm
sure many other people also from the
west came to india for such purposes the
beatles are a good example the english
rock band rock folk band abandoned the
beatles they came to india
i'm not sure if they were looking for
spiritual enlightenment i think they
were looking for inspiration from indian
music
they were aware of the fact that indian
music is way more advanced
than western music
when i say indian music i mean indian
classical music so they came to india
they
met the
sitar
practitioner
pandit ravishankar
so i think george harrison their lead
guitarist learned how to play the sitar
from ravishankar they had a good
lifelong friendship and so on so yes
many of these people from the west they
came to india in order to attain some
extra spiritual
uh
heights or to gain some kind of
knowledge which was not found in the
west and so on
and they all went back uh sufficiently
enriched culturally and spiritually
going back from india right
and when it comes to steve jobs it kind
of
influenced him very deeply the entire
indian dharmic experience when he was
diagnosed i mean after he left india he
became a vegetarian i believe vegan
vegetarian i think vegan
yes and i think he was a vegan for the
rest of his life he is officially
described in his biography as a buddhist
but well most of his experiences and
influences were hindu
but of course for the
for the sake of general platyberry
palatability they will package it as
being buddhist influences you know
buddhism is essentially hinduism
repackaged for western consumer
audiences because hinduism is too deep
too
esoteric too confusing for these small
minds so they repackage it as
buddhism so steve jobs remained a
vegetarian through the for the rest of
his life and when he was diagnosed with
cancer he tried to
have himself treated through
in in
alternative medicine i don't know it was
whether it was ayurveda or something
else he tried to
change his diet to kill the cancer and
all that so i think he took that too far
if he had not done all those
strange things he may have survived
longer maybe even beaten cancer perhaps
but he was so convinced about the power
of what he had learned in india that he
wanted to apply that even to curing
cancer unfortunately it did not work you
know
he was a really intelligent person in
that and yet he ended up making such a
silly
mistake anyhow so that's the reason why
these people
uh came to india and that's what they
learned i suppose
right let's take the next question
one second where's the next question
here's the next question
okay sunny sunny says
my question is the founder of the gupta
gupta dynasty was shri gupta
but why does all the credit go to
chandragupta the first and what was the
role of gerard kuch in the gupta dynasty
can you please explain
okay good question so the gupta empire
the gupta dynasty uh
it
was in power in
india for about nearly three centuries
right and the first the founder of the
gupta dynasty
is
a king
was a king called
sri gupta who lived in the late 3rd
century eddie
so he is the first king of the gupta
dynasty
he styled himself maharaja
his son's name was gatoth kutch
and he lived in the late 3rd century
until about 319 320 320 a.d
so that's about uh maybe 20 30 years
that he was in power again uh he styled
himself maharaja so these guys they had
a small kingdom shri gupta and his son
got garutka they both had a small
kingdom in
kind of in the region of magda
right in north northern india to the to
the eastern part of india
now the son of gatad kach happened to be
chandragupta the first but chandragupta
the first expanded his kingdom
significantly and he did not style
himself maharaja he styled himself
maharaja dhiraj
which means emperor not merely a king he
was an emperor he defeated lots of other
kings in a very short period of time he
expanded his empire his kingdom
significantly and it became so big that
he started calling himself the king of
kings emperor
maharaja raj
so so chandragupta
lived from around the reigned as emperor
from 319 a.d to around 3 350 a.d most
likely 335 or 350 there's some confusion
but some somewhere around there so the
thing is shri gupta had a small kingdom
he was content and happy with a small
kingdom his son gatok had the same small
kingdom and he was also content and
happy with that same small kingdom
chandragupta the first the grandson of
sri gupta he was not content with the
small kingdom he expanded in all
directions and he became a genuine
emperor he
transformed his ancestral little kingdom
into a proper empire and therefore we
gave credit to chandragupta why should
we give it to to shri gupta
he was the founder of the dynasty but he
did not do anything significant he had
no significant achievements and
therefore the credit goes to
chandragupta for actually
establishing
the gupta empire the dynasty was
established by sri gupta but the
empire was established by chandragupta
the first
chandragupta the first was by no means
the greatest emperor of his of his
lineage his son samudra gupta now this
is the real deal this guy his entire
career
as king as emperor was one extended
military campaign that is somewhat good
the good god what a guy he wants the
hero of a thousand battles he led from
the front he wanted war war war he
expanded in all directions he
powerful navy he used that navy to
conquer all the way to southern india
to madurai and further for the south so
in the entirety of india came under
samudragupta's
uh dominion right so he lived until
about he reigned until about 375 a.d his
son chandragupta the first expanded even
further
he conquered gandhar he conquered
bahalik
bulk
right he conquered all the
whoever was was uh ruling there
everybody trembled
at the mere
uh sound of his name he kicked out the
sketians from gujarat the maha chatrapas
and so on so you know
so
the second was also great his son kumar
gupta who did not expand the empire
further but he ruled it very steadily
and very ably
so
so that is uh
that is kumar gupta the first and kumar
gupta the kumar gupta's son was
skandagupta the great the last great
gupta emperor who repulsed wave after
wave after wave of hornic invasion in
india
he
he swore an oath that he would not sleep
on a bed and he would not eat from a
plate as long as the horns were trying
to invade india i will sleep on up on
the on the floor and i will eat from
from a leaf as long as there is a threat
to my country and he spent his whole
life fighting off the horns and he
succeeded
so as you can see
the deeds of chandragupta the first
second
are immense
compared to the deeds of shri gupta and
qatar
whose deeds actually pale in comparison
with their extraordinarily illustrious
descendants
and therefore all the credit goes to
them and not to shri gupta and to
who happen to be the first two kings
of the dynasty but not emperors by any
means right so i hope that answers your
question
all right russians
and ukrainians claim that hinduism came
from russia because of the mizzen
swastika which was found in an ivory
figurine of a female bird
which is at least 18 000 years old your
thoughts on this okay let's take a look
at what this swastika looks like
all right one second
um
let us
let me share my screen
okay ukraine swastika ukraine what what
is it the amazing swastika
let's see what it looks like
excuse me
so yeah this is the uh
alleged swastika that is found on this
bird
this uh
carving of a bird in ukraine so this is
what it looks like from the side the
bird
it's clearly uh the figurine of a bird
it's an ivory carving
this is what it looks like it's quite
small and if you look at the details of
the pattern this is what the pattern
looks like so as you can see it's not
really a swastika it's not really a
swastika it's it's some kind of
geometric worlds
that you could interpret from some
angles as something that kind of
somewhat resembles a swastika it is not
a proper swastika it is not a real
swastika it is something that is
reminiscent in some ways
of
the shape of the swastika and as you can
see the maizine carving is not a
swastikas that's what it says this
article
so uh
so it is completely incorrect to to
claim on the basis of this particular
figurine
that the swastika originates
in
ukraine or in russia and therefore
hinduism came from this region first of
all i have never made the claim
that the swastika is something that
emerged out of hinduism that is not the
case
the swastika is a
universal symbol of auspiciousness
that seems to have emerged in multiple
parts of the world apparently
simultaneously
it seems to have
emerged
more than 10 000 years ago
right
today
if you look at the prevalence of the
swastika today you will find it is
prevalent only
mostly in the dharmic world which is
india
the various buddhist nations of
southeast asia hindu buddhist nations of
southeast asia
china tibet indonesia
burma thailand etc right laos vietnam
and so on also in korea also in japan
and in mongolia as well in japan even
today if you go to google maps you will
find that
temples shinto and buddhist temples are
marked with swastikas
so uh
that's where the swastika is prevalent
today
and therefore it is uh some people
kind of make the claim that it
originated in hinduism or in the dharmic
religions with dharmic culture which is
not the case you will find swastikas
even in africa
you will find swastika motifs even in
north america and south america among
the indigenous peoples of america in
their artwork even in their ancient
stone carvings and all so on like that
so it appears that this
symbol of auspiciousness was universally
prevalent across the planet
and it emerged
apparently simultaneously a very long
time ago
right
uh and and this bird that they talk
about this mazin bird swastika carving
thing it's not 18 000 years old it's
about i don't know 14 15 000 years old
roughly i'm saying give or take a couple
of thousand years maybe here and there
so
and therefore this does not constitute
any kind of proof that hinduism came
from outside of india right because
swastika is not exclusive to hinduism it
was prevalent in many cultures many many
cultures in the past among the romans
among the crete people of crete among
the minoans among the ancient greeks
we
you find swastikas in the ancient city
of
hisarlik ilyan troy
in the ruins of troy
and in so many other places
right
so it is not something that's exclusive
to hinduism and therefore if you find an
ancient swastika somewhere else it
doesn't mean hinduism came from there
there's no correlation
and it's very interesting to speculate
as to how did this
this geometrical figure the swastika
become so prevalent
globally
and become a universal symbol of
auspiciousness that may have something
to do with an ancient
astronomical event it's something that
we can discuss
separately
but i hope this answers the question
karthik says recently a report came from
the government that the reason for the
cbs helicopter crash is bad weather what
are your views on it
see i had answered a question about the
about the helicopter crash of general b
pinzing ravath
and i had said that an investigation
will be done the very thorough
investigation will be done
uh the um the cause of the
of the
air crash will be uncertain
but it will not it will not be
communicated to the people
so the thing is this
india is a nation that has lots of
enemies we know that we have enemies
beyond our borders but the bigger
problem is we have lots of way more
enemies within our own borders people
who do not consider themselves indians
people who hate their own country and
people who work for certain external
forces
and such people are even in positions of
great power i'm not pointing figures at
anybody in particular but
this is indeed the case
so if you really make if you make the
real
uh
results of your investigation public
then your enemies will come to know what
you have found and therefore it doesn't
make sense to do that
so i had said that they will find the
real cause but they will communicate
something uh
something not very specific to the
public you know something like
it's it was
either
the best the best thing to say is bad
bad weather bad weather contributed to
the to the crash
so we have to take this
with in under advisement we have to take
this with a grain of salt
it does not make any sense for the armed
forces in the government to reveal
the real cause of the crash to our
enemies we don't want them to know what
we know
and therefore
it is
it is expected i i am i was not
surprised at all when this
statement was made that the
crash was caused by bad
weather the actual cause of the crash is
in my opinion something else i don't
have the answer
i don't have inside information but i am
certain that bad weather is not the
cause of the crash
this helicopter is
built to withstand any kind of bad
brother it's a military helicopter it's
one of the top of the shelf military
helicopters it can take rpg fire rocket
propelled grenade fire so what about a
little bit of bad weather come on
so i think there's something else that
happened and
so the government
by now knows what really happened the
army by now knows what really happened
uh
the intelligence apparatus of the
country knows what's happened and i hope
that
whoever has done this will be
will be dealt with
and will be uh
and justice will be meted out to the to
whoever has done this whoever the powers
are
because it's not the first time
something
like this has happened in india
yeah that's all i can say
for now so you know that's my view about
this karan says why do ancient brahmins
why do why did ancient brahmins
use sanskrit and vedas for themselves
and not for all people so my dear friend
karan where did you get this information
that ancient brahmins were so powerful
they kept sanskrit in the vedas only for
themselves
and they forced everybody to to speak
other languages and read other books
where do you get such nonsensical
information my dear friend
who taught you this
was it your school teacher your class
teacher your history teacher was it your
ncaa textbooks
or was it
your favorite tv serial
or was it your favorite news channel who
taught you this nonsense
what evidence do you have that ancient
brahmins use sanskrit and vedas only for
themselves
and not for all people
if there is no source for this claim
then how can you make this claim
right
there is no evidence there is not a
single shred of evidence
that corroborates what you have claimed
and this is something i see all the time
brahmins are evil brahmins did this
brahmins did that
you know in the ancient days
who wielded the power do you know where
power comes from
said power comes from the barrel of a
gun in ancient times there were no guns
but there was the blade of a sword
so the power in the ancient days came
from the blade of the sword and who
wielded the swords was it the brahmanas
who wielded the swords
no it was not the brahmins who wielded
the swords it was the khatriyas who
wielded the swords
they are the guys who had the power not
the brahmanas the brahmins were
powerless they were mere advisors
they could be over ruled anytime
if the khatri has so wished but india's
society was harmonious it was a very
well functioning society for thousands
of years and therefore
the brahmins at their place the katrias
they have their place everybody had
their place and everybody everybody
contributed to a harmonious society but
today the marxist historians wanted to
believe that brahmins
were the evil guys
the objective is to destroy hinduism and
the
keepers and preservers of the knowledge
are the brahmanas and therefore if you
want to destroy hinduism
you have to attack the brahmanas and
that's why these
these stories are perpetuated including
in our textbooks these days and then
people come up with these questions i
don't blame you for believing this but
you know
use your brain
you know how things were right what you
what you are taught is that we had
forecasts
four rigid castes
the brahmins had the books the chatris
of the swords and whatever else
so the guys who had the swords could the
brahmins ever have forced them to do to
do whatever
if the trees wanted to study sanskrit in
the vedas could the brahmins have
prevented them
but no all brains have been switched off
we just don't think anymore
okay avinash says was the big was the
excuse me excuse me
was the big bang a white hole
right so what's a white hole let's begin
with the white hole uh we have spoken
about the big bang i think a million
times by now so i'm sure everybody knows
what the big bang was like roughly right
the beginning of the of the universe the
births of the universe
so the big bang was a singularity
and everything came out of the
singularity
so the entire universe that we perceive
around us
it was all within the singularity
and then the singularity expanded
space-time expansion it was not an
explosion it was an expansion and that
is the big bang it's called the big bang
the name is misleading
now what's a white hole
a white hole is the exact opposite of a
black hole so let's say you have a black
hole sitting here right
a good nice black hole sitting here in
space
and
any object in its vicinity is going to
be attracted towards it by the force of
gravity because a
black hole is a very powerful
gravitational pull
and if you're close enough then you're
going to be sucked into it eventually
so
in the future anything that's near the
black hole is going to end up inside the
black hole no a white hole is a certain
set of solutions of the einstein
equations which are the exact opposite
of a black hole so
if you look at
if you if you
look at time flowing near a black hole
and if you take a video let's say you
will set it slowly slowly everything
goes towards the black hole and is
eventually sucked into it right
if you do the same thing with the white
hole you will see time flowing in
reverse essentially everything is being
pushed out from the white hole a white
hole is something that spews things
outward not inward like a black hole so
it's like it's like the mirror opposite
of a black hole uh
so that's what it is
and
the thing about a white hole is that it
expels
matter into space time right into space
so whatever is being ejected from a
white hole it goes into space
but in the case of the big bang
there was nothing outside the
singularity
when the singularity expanded that's
what gave rise to space time
so that is the key difference between a
white hole and the big bang it sounds
like a white hole but a white hole is
inside space-time
but black hole
but the
but the singularity of the big bang
itself contained all of the space time
that we see around us in the observable
universe so a white hole isn't so the
big bang was not a white hole it was not
it was something completely different to
see to understand what it is you need to
look at the
standard model and uh yeah standard
model standard model cosmology
so in short the big bang was not a white
hole
all right what's the next question
yes this is by javed mustafa
mughals and delhi sultans made india
their home lived and died here
chingas khan knew no principles even
changed khan praised jalaluddin for his
bravery
okay the first statement is the mughals
and delhi sultans made india their home
lived and died there you know my dear
friend javed how about i come to your
house i make it my house
huh
and i live there and die there and
impose my will upon whoever is living in
your house would you like it my dear
friend
these mughals and delhi did they come to
india after applying for a visa
who gave the permission to make india
their home
did the people of india want these
barbarians
in their home
no
so please
just because they came to india and made
it their home doesn't make them some
great
paradigms of virtue and secularism they
were terrorists barbarians not because
of the religion because of their
behavior
nobody is a barbarian by blood or by
religion
you are a barber not you
i don't mean you
a person
is a barbarian only by their actions not
by their blood or by their religion by
their actions and by the actions of the
delhi sultans and the turko mughals and
all these
invaders the turkic invaders they were
all barbarians they behaved in a brutal
bastille way
in a bastille manner they were all
barbarians
and terrorists therefore the war that's
the that's part one genghis khan knew no
principle blah blah blah blah blah
no examples given and even changes khan
praised jalaluddin that's what you say
let me explain the bravery of jalal
geraldine kharismi
was the last
sultan of harassment he was hated by his
own brother
he was hated by his own grandmother
she preferred to be captured by the
mughals by the mongols than to go with
her grandson
uh in his uh
bid to escape the great shri changes
khan so this coward jalaluddin he left
his grandmother behind he took some of
his uh
close relatives and their wives and all
the women folk and whatever was left of
his army and he tried to escape to india
he made it to india he crossed the hindu
came into afghanistan gandhar which was
then india
and he went further south into punjab
and that's where he was that's where
chinese khan caught up with him on the
banks of the sindhu river
that's where the great uh not great the
battle of the indus happened 800 years
ago
800 years and some months ago
in the year 12 21 in the winter of 1221
and jalaluddin's army was totally
annihilated and we know what jalaluddin
did the great brave jalaluddin what he
did he left his wives concubines and
family behind
and he crossed the river and escaped
with his life
do you think his khan would praise him
for this bravery
for leaving his women folk and family
behind
to be enslaved by the mongols do you
really think chung is khan
would have praised jalaluddin for the
act of cowardice
come on
i just don't get it why these people
want to want to portray jalaluddin as a
great
brave paradigm of
of courage and bravery
in this story there is this persistent
story that chingus khan praised
jalaluddin and said that every father
should have a son like this you know
where this story comes from it comes
from the islamic historian jawaini
juwani was a persian historian
i i believe it was juani who came up
with this fictitious story and joanie
was not even present there during the
battle of the power of the indus he
wasn't even there
you know there is not a single authentic
court of chingiskan that has survived
until today there are many apocryphal
tales about the khan said this in
chinese
said that the only true record of his
life
that is reliable is the secret history
of the mongols which does not contain a
single quote for from chinese khan
everything else is hearsay you know what
they say in hindi kahi suni bate that's
what it is so please stop lying about
jalaluddin the coward he was a
coward par excellence
okay this is by andre from canada uh you
okay what's the question you have made a
quick case for the case that shingis
khan had principles
but did he hold his sons to those same
principles
he certainly would have had the power to
do so but did he
if he did not then i would suggest that
those principles were not really
principles all right
a fair point
so
we know that chinggis khan treated his
sons no different from any other soldier
in his army
of course they were all princes and they
were all
destined to have kingdoms of their own
so what he did is that he
put his various sons under the tutelage
of various generals of his for instance
his eldest son jochi
whose paternity was under question by
the way
his eldest son jochi was put under the
tutelage of the great subudai
subutai was one of the greatest mongol
generals of all time much of what
chingis khan achieved was because of the
uh
brilliance
of the general subutai
so
changiskan's eldest son jochi was put
under the tutelage of sabotage and they
were sent on a scouting mission
westwards
they scouted around the kokasas region
they they
went did a complete uh circum
circumnavigation of the caspian sea i
believe
uh they even scouted in parts of russia
and so on there were battles and
skirmishes but there was this was not a
mission of conquest it was a mission of
scouting to see what else is out there
that we don't know about and jochi
participated in this and various other
sons of chinese participated in various
military campaigns under
the tutelage of various
generals and various armed divisions of
the mongol
army so ching is khan did put all of his
sons in harm's way
it was for them to survive or not if
they survived then they were worthy of
being
hans in their own right when the time
came and of course they would have to
obey all the um
all the rules
that every mongol soldier had to obey
there was no exception made for
chingaskhan's
sons so i would say that he uh held his
sons to the same principle that every
other mongol soldier was was held into
his own
principles now after he died things
changed right
after chinese khan died his son ogoda
khan became the overall great khan
of the mongols and various other sons of
his were given big parcels of land in
the four corners of the mongol empire
and then they went their own way
that's how the mongol empire eventually
fragmented
because they did not quite follow the
principles
of their father they some of them
conquered without need to without any
real need for
conquering for instance stringish khan
conquered only when there were just
causes for war he went to war only when
there was a genuine need to retaliate
against some kind of
wrongdoing
in the case of his sons they conquered
just because they could so that is one
difference between genghis khan and his
sons and that's how things are changed
after chingashan's death but i would say
that he as long as he was alive he held
everybody to the same principles and
his rule was a rule of
merit it was a meritocracy nobody was
given any undue favors
as monsters under whom their countries
became hellholes
some google pictures show the opposite
of this your views on these two
different people
please i would not characterize their
countries as hell holes
while those two guys were in power look
at
look at the record of saddam hussein
yes there's no doubt he was a dictator
there's no doubt it was a brutal
dictator you know what
every country has its own customs
every country has its own culture it is
just futile to try and impose the same
system on every country which is kind of
what's happening today everybody needs
to have democracy
arabah
some cultures
simply
uh
democracy simply doesn't work in some
cultures some people are just too
violent and some too brutal some
cultures are such that you need
a heavy hand to rule over them
and
if you look at the past
four five thousand years of history in
the middle east you see the same old
thing
beheadings warfare
and so on and so forth you know it's
always been the same
during the time of king
of various kings of mesopotamia
what are the names sargon of akkad king
rimosh
uh
ashurbanipal ashor nasir baal and so on
and so forth it's always been brutality
this region has a history of brutality
no matter what religion was in was in
vogue it's always been a brutal place
and when you have people who are
accustomed to that sort of brutal
life
for 5 000 years you need a certain kind
of ruler to
keep law and order right
and i think saddam hussein is is
something that emerged out of the milieu
in mesopotamia in in
iraq
and he did what he had to do to impose
law and order upon his people
he knew what kind of people his people
were
right
and if you look at the record
if you look at the kind of
governance that he established
it was
i mean during his rule
iraq was very peaceful iraq was very
orderly there was law in order there was
justice maybe the justice was brutal but
it was effective
and uh
and
what you also had was that women
were quite empowered
and there was no sectarian strife
sunni was a shia
versus arab none of that nonsense was
tolerated under saddam hussein
women
had equal rights as men
and iraq was truly a secular state
doesn't matter what your religion was
even if you're a christian it did not
matter
right everybody got the same treatment
so it was actually a well oiled well
well functioning society
and then what do the americans do
they bomb democracy to iraq and look at
iraq today it is a hell hole today it
was not a hell hole under saddam yes i
am sure there was oppression of certain
people and he
and so on so forth he was a brutal
dictator
that's just how it is that's how it has
always been in the middle east you think
the arab states are different the arab
countries do you think they are
different do you think iran is different
come on
so that's how it was and similarly for
uh
for libya
muammar gaddafi
you know the americans have always
portrayed him as a monster and
eventually they got to him they had him
bumped off in the most atrocious way
imaginable whatever you know
you live with the sword you die by the
sword that's how it goes but
even if you look at libya under gaddafi
it was a reasonably orderly place there
was law and order brutal heavy-handed
law and order but it was still there and
after
the death the the
death execution whatever you want to
call it of muhammad gaddafi see what
hell
libya has descended into there are open
slave markets in libya today
excuse me
slave markets human smuggling what not
there's no actual government there's no
law and order today it's a hell hole but
apparently they have elections there
yes democracy wins
excuse me
so that's the truth
you know every country doesn't need
democracy every country has its own
customs and it's just wrong to try to
impose western values and western ways
of doing things on countries
that well don't need that
so one pratihar says uh as a quantum
physicist what's your opinion on how
homeopathic medicines work
okay here we go lots of people are gonna
hate me now
i think homeopathy is a joke first of
all there is a distinction between
homeopathy and ayurveda homeopathy is
not ayurveda today in india i think lots
of people believe it's the same thing
it's not
homeopathy is something that emerged out
of 19th or 18th century germany i think
i think it came from europe most likely
in germany most likely in the 19th
century
some
stupid uh pseudoscientific concepts
um i don't even know what those are but
essentially homeopathic is a homeopathy
is about very very low
doses of whatever
substance you're ingesting you know it's
called a homeopathic dose which means it
is essentially useless
so do homeopathic medicines work no they
don't work it doesn't work at all
and i'm sure that i'm gonna get lots of
booze for this but come on
packed a fact
so it's nothing to do with the quantum
being a quantum physicist or any such
thing but it's just a scientific known
fact that the
those ages are so low that it simply
can't work you know in homeopathy
and the principles are also not really
not quite scientific
okay uh help from the west is not the
right answer they help for the reason
read this book startup nation so i had i
have a
video clip about a clip about israel
why does tiny israel dominate the entire
middle east
and i said one of the reasons for
israel's success is that it has been
given
it has received a lot of aid from the
west
mostly from the united states but also
from the jewish diaspora across the
western
the western world right so this
gentleman says
help from the west is not the right
answer read the hell for a reason
read the book startup nation
so this is see no
no i'm not trying to
make fun of this gentleman but this is
an example of too little knowledge and
thinking you know everything
if you talk about yes israel is a
startup nation today there is this very
famous book called startup nation but do
you think israel was a startup nation in
israel was a ragtag
new nation
barely surviving
and it was beset by enemies on all sides
there were no startups at that time sir
so
try you have to look at history from a
larger perspective with the proper
nuance proper context
okay you read a book called startup
nation and you think that the west helps
israel and invest there because there
are startups array baba i'm talking
about the whole history of israel from
its inception there were no startups at
the time
israel was struggling for survival
and it survived because of aid from the
jewish diaspora across europe and the us
and also
because of aid from western countries
eventually to a large extent from the
united states
that is the correct answer so if you
have read one book it doesn't give you
all the knowledge please do not have
this attitude that i read this therefore
i know everything
i don't think i know everything at all
i am always eager to learn more and i i
see people like this
saying no you are wrong
read this book then you will have all
the knowledge come on please
please please don't have this sort of
attitude it's it's going to hurt you in
the long run
wow long question
my name is fatima i'm from kerala i have
a request can you please make a video
about champakraman pillai
the forgotten freedom fighter who first
used the slogan joy hint he asked help
from the imperial germany
and during 194 later in 1934 he was
assassinated by hitler's nazi police
he asked aid from the german empire he
was involved in bombarding british ships
at madras port et cetera et cetera et
cetera all that all right
so uh who was champa garam and pillai he
was a freedom fighter
he was a member of the provincial
government in 1990 not thereabouts
so this government was set up in
kabul was it in afghanistan certainly
with the help of the germans
he was part of a group of freedom
fighters in berlin i believe
at some point in time
very interesting person and like you say
it looks like he was assassinated or
poisoned he was poisoned
by the germans because for whatever
reason he was no longer very convenient
for them
and it looks like i mean it is alleged
that he was part of a german warships
raid on the the port of madras
the german battle cruiser uh mdn like
you say most likely
and this ship raided the port of madras
opened fire and did some damage
around the time of the first world war i
believe so i don't have all the dates
and all the details in mind but yes this
gentleman is very interesting he had a
very adventurous life
died young
most likely assassinated by the nazis so
yeah i could certainly
look deeper into this in the future and
maybe make a separate video about it
so yeah
anime says
do you think authors and researchers
today have more access and freedom to
study
and write about history than in the
gandhi nerubian era oh for sure
for sure first of all we did not have
the internet in those days
and there was there were so many
academic restrictions and government
restrictions on people
um
you were not allowed to do certain kinds
of research if you were a professor and
if you did the wrong kind of if you had
the wrong kinds of inclinations you
would be
marginalized or you would lose your job
and that sort of thing
there'd be all kinds of harassment this
is a story that has happened over and
over again in the indian academia
even if you managed to write a book you
would find no publishers
so that's
something that was very much common in
the gandhi nehru
and overall congress regime era you know
i think the situation has changed only
after 2014 more or less you know that
people have been able to speak openly
about
a variety of things so yes i agree
there's more freedom now
and we should cherish the freedom
okay wisdom bro says apart from its
geographical location why does every
country pay attention to djibouti these
days
well to explain i will obviously have to
go to the map right
so let us pull up a map
the map
excuse me
so this is the world and let's go to
djibouti so where is djibouti it's right
here see
if you see my mouse pointer i'm pointing
in india now if you go
west southwest from mumbai let's say
across the so-called arabian sea you
come to the gulf of aden here
if you go further west you come to
djibouti this little tiny country here
is called
now why is this country why is there
like you say attention to this place so
first of all you have the baba al-mandeb
here
for ins let me show you what it is
so if you look at this narrow straight
here
this is called the baba al-mandab strait
and this is the most likely location
across which
the last great out of africa migration
happened the last great
migration of homo sapiens about 75 000
years ago
most likely happened from here
so that is the uh that is the
migration that gave rise to the human
population
which exists out of africa today
and this migration is believed to have
happened about 75 000 years before today
from here so that is one reason why
djibouti is interesting for many people
especially for
historians geneticist anthropologist and
so on
the second reason
the more pertinent reason
why djibouti is so interesting let us
let us go into it right
so
let's find the satellite image
excuse me
let's go deeper into djibouti city
so here you have the djibouti ambula
international airport it's just an
international airport but not quite
let's go deeper into this place
so if you look at the aircraft here
there is something okay there is
something called camp limoney here
which is a us military base if you look
at the aircraft sitting on this
tarmac these are american military
aircraft as you can see let's see some
more aircraft let's see what else do we
have
there have to be more
check this out
again american military aircraft sitting
there
do we have any more
let's see what we have here these seem
to be civilian aircraft over here
most likely
this again is an american military
aircraft so as you can see this is a us
military base air force base it is used
for uh
domestic i mean no not domestic for
civilian civilian air traffic but again
you can see
military aircraft over here so this is a
us air force base it's not only
a u.s air force base
there's something else as well here
if you see this
if you see this aircraft it's most
likely a japanese military aircraft
and
if you see here
this is a japanese military base
it's the only
japanese military base outside of
japanese soil djiboti
so right here this aircraft this airport
is home to
an american air force base and a
japanese
military base
let's look further at djibouti
what else do we have we have another
airport here chabelle airport right
that's what it says now let's look at
the kind of aircraft you have sitting
here
let's see do we have an aircraft oh yeah
i can see something here
now what do these aircraft look like
don't these aircraft look like predator
predator drones
the unmanned aerial vehicles that the
americans operate
long long term loitering aircraft that
loiter for hours and hours at an
altitude of 10 11 000 kilo meters not
kilometers meters
so as you can see this is another us
military base they seem to be flying
drones from here and maybe something
else that may not be visible to us
so this is the second airbase that the
americans use now that's not the end of
the story let's look here
what do we find here
this is a chinese people's liberation
army
naval base
isn't it strange you have a
couple of us bases a japanese base and a
chinese base as well
weird
so this entire facility here
is a chinese naval base
in such an interesting location
right in a key location it's kind of
located at this uh choke point
this naval choke point so that is the
reason why djibouti is interesting
and why every country pays attention to
djibouti these days i just showed you a
very brief overview from the from the
map
about what's going on there so yeah it's
an interesting place isn't it
okay radha update says uh when we search
on the internet about maps or world maps
in the images section the map of india
is rarely shown correctly we have
territorial disputes in exciting and
poke but still those are not part of
either china or pakistan
and so on so forth should our government
take strong actions against those
websites who show our map incorrectly or
else what should be our take on this
you know there are millions of websites
in the world you think of our government
at the time
you do you think about the government as
a time and the bandwidth
to go and search every website in demand
that you correct the map no it's a waste
of time
our energy and our effort should be
spent
in correcting the facts on the ground
they are showing these
what you call incorrect maps of india
because what they sure reflect reflects
the ground reality
whether we like it or not
the portions of the map that are shown
is not part of india are currently
occupied by these foreign countries
either pakistan in tokyo
gilgit
or china aksai chin
and various other parts
these are currently under foreign
occupation
and that's why these websites they just
show what reflects the ground reality so
india
instead of wasting its time trying to
fight every single website owner what
india should do
is try to correct the facts on the
ground
now that's gonna take some doing that's
gonna take some time but that is where
our energy and efforts should be focused
not on fighting various anonymous
website owners
karthik says can you please tell us
about the silurian hypothesis
right the silurian hypothesis
excuse me one second
so imagine you're living
in a house on on rent
lots of people live on rent right
so when you live in a house on rent
and it's a
it's not a brand new house then it means
that
before you lived there
some other people lived there and these
people you never you will most likely
never know who they were
and sometimes it may be so that
such people lived there for like two
three decades
and the house was theirs and now you're
occupying that
it's possible right
similarly isn't it possible that the
planet will live on the planet we live
in
was long ago occupied
by some other civilization
not aliens but a civilization that
emerged on our own planet
maybe a few hundred million years before
today
they emerged they lived for a long time
and then for whatever reason they
disappeared
now we know for a fact that tectonic
activity
is such that it kind of erases all
traces
of what happened on the surface every
few hundred million years
or even every few million years
so for instance we don't find traces of
dinosaurs on the surface mostly
except in
very select locations that are exposed
to the uh air
but typically you have to dig for
dinosaur fossils right and the dinosaurs
died out about 65 million years before
today
now imagine if if a
intelligent species or civilization
existed on the planet a billion years
before today
would we find any trace of that no
because tectonic activity would have
ensured that everything would have gone
underground long long long ago under the
oceans under the ground
and we may never ever be able to find
traces of that
see our planet is about
four and a half billion years old
billion with a b
and life
as we know it has exist existed on the
planet for about three and a half
billion years the earliest
incontrovertible
evidence for life goes back about three
and a half billion years before today
so that has given
plenty of time for many civilizations to
rise and fall and we may never know
about any of them in in case there was
any intelligent civilization that
existed before us
so that is the cellular hypothesis that
maybe
there was
an intelligent civilization of of beings
on our planet
just as intelligent as us who had an
extensive urban
globe spanning civilization just like
what we have today and for whatever
reason maybe an asteroid strike maybe a
commentary strike maybe climate change
whatever
for some reason they all died out
and over the
hundreds of millions of years and
billions of years all traces of their
evidence has been eroded away and
buried underground because of tectonic
activity it is
very
plausible that such a scenario could
have happened
so that's what we call the silurian
hypothesis and there is something we
have to take seriously
arjun says do you think space x will
become the next space superpower if it
gets more funding
do you think space
space x lacks funding
do you think spacex is not a space
superpower
let me give you a statistic
spacex
launches more rockets per month
than isro launches in a whole year
digest that
spacex launches more rockets in a single
month than isro launches in us in a
whole year sometimes in two years
and the kinds of the kind of rockets
that spacex launches are
orders of magnitude more powerful than
the most powerful slow powerful isro
lock rocket
the gslv mark iii
and spacex is currently developing the
most powerful rocket in human history
so space x is the 10 000 ton gorilla in
the room it's bigger than nasa it's
bigger than lockheed martin
it's bigger than the united launch
alliance it's bigger than the russians
it's bigger than the chinese it's bigger
than everybody else already it is
already the biggest
space launching power in the world it is
already a super power it doesn't lack
anything
right they are building multiple rockets
at any given point in time how many
rockets is for building right now
yeah it's just uh
it's sad when you try to compare isro
with these companies and the thing is
isro has been around since how long 70s
1970s
spacex
is a company that
was born in the 2000s it nearly went
bankrupt so many times multiple times it
was on the brink of disaster for such a
long period of time
it was one rocket failure away from
closing permanently
and
it managed to survive and now it's
thriving so that's how you do it
that's the kind of ambition and drive
and focus you need if you want to if you
want to succeed
one would love to see that in india in
israel but
it's not this scientist's fault in
israel
because they don't control their budgets
they don't control the funding they
don't control the direction of their
work
it's the government that does it
um okay next question priyanka says
what's your opinion on the latest
cryptocurrency craze will it be good or
bad for the future
how will the world
change will it get rid of banks as
middlemen
will it control inflation globally
please share your opinion
so it's too early to tell but you know
from the reactions of various
governments who are trying to regulate
the cryptocurrency uh
the entire paradigm of cryptocurrency
you can see that governments are worried
because governments want to regulate
things they want a control as you can
see during the pandemic they want
control they're trying to acquire more
and more control over the people over
everything in their lives
and cryptocurrency especially the
blockchain technology is something that
will take away control from the
governments because it will decentralize
everything
and the banks will no longer be able to
act as middlemen in rake in all the
profits right
so the chinese have banned
cryptocurrency india wants to ban
cryptocurrency and so on and so forth so
in a way it's good if cryptocurrency is
there
because it
removes all the
it takes away the power from the
middlemen the banks the corporates right
uh it can also control inflation but
well to some extent
so for ins for instance
there are multiple
block versions of blockchain in the
market today so blockchain technology
i'm not going to explain what it is it
will be a whole different thing
but for instance bitcoin
um
it's blocked see blick bitcoin has no
boss bitcoin has no owner
the blockchain is public
and
bitcoin
it has a finite number so there's only a
five finite number of bitcoins which
means that you cannot keep printing new
bitcoins as and when you like
which means bitcoin is exactly the same
as digital gold
it has a finite value you cannot put in
more just to make more money and so on
so that's why bitcoin is good now look
if you look at ethereum
ethereum does have an owner
and ethereum can be minted
you can create more ethereum if you want
so you know it all depends not every
cryptocurrency is the panacea for all
the ills
and
so it's still kind of like a wild west
kind of situation
uh lots of people are diving into this
lots of new cryptocurrencies are being
created you give me two two months i
could create uh code my own blockchain
and issue my own
cryptocurrency chavda coin would you
like that
that sort of thing you know so right now
it's kind of murky and confusing
but if it is done right then it can
certainly empower lots of people
uh
so yeah it it could possibly good would
be good and it could also be dangerous
for government for instance uh there are
lots of
uses of of cryptocurrency that can help
anti-national
activities terrorist activities and so
on you know
so there are good reasons for
governments to be worried but there are
also a good uses of bitcoin and also bad
news like everything else
so that's where right now i think in the
future it may be
regulated to a great extent and we'll
have to see
okay
uh deelon the silva says what do you
think about general naravane's statement
on kashmir in which he said that he's
not averse to demilitarizing chen
do you think it will be a good choice to
choose him as a cds listen
he is not making a statement in a
personal capacity
he he's not a school boy who doesn't
know what to say and what not to say
right when he makes any statement
it's a statement on behalf of the indian
government and the indian army it's a
statement that has been vetted already
and i think the media has
kind of blown this out of proportion
excuse me
this statement has been blown out of
proportion he is not in any way
suggesting that we are going to just
leave seattle and give it over to the
pakistanis
what he actually said that is that the
indian government in our army is not
averse
to the
idea
of demilitarizing sea chin sometime in
the future
if
these these these conditions are met
that's what he meant and what conditions
should be met that the current
demarcation boundary between the indian
uh
territory indian health territory in the
pakistani health territory should be
formalized in in a treaty
and then both sides should withdraw and
this withdrawal should be properly
monitored and
all that sort of thing so there need to
be need to be checks and measures and
all those things
in that case we may possibly perhaps in
the future consider
demilitarizing crg that's the kind of
statement he made he's not saying
we're going to make it we're going to
make it happen tomorrow
he also did not say it's my personal
opinion that we want to we should leave
none of these statements is correct but
that's the way the media portrays things
right
so that's what i can say about this now
it has nothing to do with him being a
good choice or bad judge for a cds
that's for the government to decide i am
kind of perplexed that we still haven't
chosen the cds i believe in in a
well-oiled machine in a well-oiled
system
when you have a cds you should have
number two number three number four at
least three four people waiting in line
in case any unforeseen thing happens to
immediately become the next cds and and
take things forward it's kind of
surprising that the next cds has still
not been chosen
but well let's see how
that goes
okay let me take one more question for
today
this is by profile you said that the
that electoral system slows the country
down and pulls it down so why canada
australia and new zealand are prosperous
nations
and are still growing in democracy
please tell us the truth behind their
systems and as well
see
i said
an electoral system with every elections
every four years and state elections
every one or two years and all that
slows down the country
i spoke about the governance of a
country not the economy of a country
right of course it will have economic
impact as well
now
so you say that canada australia and new
zealand etcetera are prosperous nations
they are still doing well despite
democracy
here's a question for you my friend
did these countries become prosperous
because of democracy
what is the source
the root
of the prosperity
of canada australia new zealand the
united states how did these nations and
uk as well how did these nations become
prosperous
are you trying to say they became
prosperous because they have democracy
no
they became process the uk became
prosperous because of its plunder of
india
45 trillion dollars worth of plunder
that's why the uk became prosperous
because of theft
plunder
how did
the u.s and canada become prosperous
well the us is stolen territory stolen
from the from the natives canada is
stolen territory stolen from the natives
it is the
europeans
the the british the british the english
who stole this entire continent from the
natives
and then planned it it's still being
plundered for resources
so that's where the immense wealth comes
from
they got an entire continent for free
they stole an entire continent from
their from the true owners
a very rich continent
the real owners the real natives had
never plundered the land that's why the
land was so fertile and so full of
natural resources and gifts
and that is the source of the prosperity
of the united states and canada same
goes for australia and new zealand these
are stolen
australia and new zealand are also
stolen lands australia is a stolen
continent new zealand is a beautiful
rich fabulously resource rich
two islands that again has been stolen
from the natives that is the source of
the prosperity not your democracy
it's not democracy that has made the
west prosperous
it is theft loot village plunder that
has made the west prosperous and now
democracy is slowly slowly
uh
well
you know when they stole all this all
this
territory and all this wealth they were
not democratic countries those were they
were mostly monarchies and autocratic
countries at the time now you have
democracy and you can see that these
nations are still slowly slowly
towards civil war
whether you like it or not
so that is the truth
behind their systems
shall we take one more question for
today
all right
um anuj says what are your thoughts
about the lca pages its capabilities and
how it's compared
to its rival and the first channel that
it's not being a good fighter and its
impact on the indian aviation industry i
think this is a brilliant fighter jet
small lightweight fighter very capable
fourth generation fighter
and you know the best thing about the
lcds
we designed and developed it
developed it ourselves yes it's a it's
the first fighter in a very long time
we've developed
but
our capabilities matured our design and
development and manufacturing
capabilities matured as a result
of building a fighter jet that actually
flies and actually performs quite well
so now the newer iterations the lca mark
ii
lca mark 1 a lca mark ii are going to be
even better and then we're gonna base a
whole
different uh
bunch of jets on them
on the basic design of the lca
you have the twin engine deck based
fighter t e d b f
you have the amca
the advanced
medium combat aircraft and then you have
the uh
i think there's one more
fighter jet that we are
designing so these are all going to
benefit from all the pain and
frustration that our engineers and
scientists had to go through while
making the pages uh top class
uh combat worthy aircraft so we will not
have to reinvent the
wheel all over again for these new
aircraft so that is the real value of
the pages
we
put in place all the technologies we
developed all the technologies from
scratch most of them the the radar the
avionics
the fuselage and so many other things
and now we have the knowledge the
know-how of how to take that to the next
level
so that is the real um
value of all the pain that our people
went went through
the all the delays that we had are
because of politicians they kept
changing the specifications right
otherwise we would have had they just
flying 20 years before before it did but
anyhow whatever happened happened and
now we can take the
next steps in
building a fifth generation aircraft
which will come up in the next 10 10
years or so
okay my dear friends i'm gonna end this
session right here
and uh
so thank you for all the questions and i
will see you tomorrow in a live chat
session
so until then take care and i will see
you tomorrow thank you bye